<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 id="c.1" type="chapter" n="1" org="uniform" sample="complete"> 
<head>The schools and schoolmasters of Colonial days in <placeName reg="Medford">Medford</placeName>.<note anchored="yes" place="unspecified">

<milestone unit="sentence" n="1" /> 
<p>read before the <rs>Medford</rs> <orgName n="Historical Society" type="society">Historical Society</orgName>.</p></note></head> <docAuthor>by <persName n="Morrison,,Benjamin,F.,," id="n0334.0002.00000.00001" reg="default:Morrison,Benjamin,F.,," authname="morrison,benjamin,f."><foreName n="Benjamin" full="yes">Benj.</foreName> <foreName full="yes">F.</foreName> <surname full="yes">Morrison</surname></persName>.</docAuthor> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="2" />owing to the fact that allusions to the subject of education in its early records are very few and very meagre, comparatively little can now be said with certainty of <placeName reg="Medford">Medford</placeName> schools and schoolmasters during the <name>Colonial</name> period.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="3" />We do know, however, that amid privation and poverty and constant warfare, not only with a harsh climate, but with <q direct="unspecified">savage beasts and still more savage men,</q> they were laying the foundations of that which we, their descendants, are now richly enjoying.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="4" />Their children are left to estimate the greatness of their labors by the grandeur of the results which have flowed from them.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="5" />No commonwealth like <placeName reg="Massachusetts" key="tgn,7007517" authname="tgn,7007517">Massachusetts</placeName> can spring up and grow to its present proud position without an adequate cause; and among those who did their share of the work and bore their share of the burdens we may be sure were the early settlers of <placeName reg="Medford">Medford</placeName>.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="6" />A prominent and discriminating writer has said that <q direct="unspecified">everything which has power to win the respect and command the obedience of men must have its roots deep in the past.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="7" />As with our political institutions so with our schools and educational system generally; they were a copy, more or less exact, of what the people had left behind in Old England.</q>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="8" /></p> 
<p>The statement is frequently made that by the law of <dateStruct value="1647--" full="yes" authname="1647"><year reg="1647" full="yes">1647</year></dateStruct> <placeName reg="Massachusetts" key="tgn,7007517" authname="tgn,7007517">Massachusetts</placeName> established the <num value="1" type="ordinal">first</num> system of free <pb id="p.2" n="2" /> public schools in the world.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="9" />But this is hardly true.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="10" />They were public schools, and many of them were free; but the law made their support permissive rather than compulsory, and direct taxation for their support was by no means universal.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="11" />In very many cases the town rate, that is, the general tax, was only to supplement other sources of income; and it took many years to make apparent that <q direct="unspecified">tuition fees from the rich and free tuition for the poor made class distinctions too pronounced in a new society where in church and state all were equal.</q>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="12" /></p> 
<p>We must not forget, moreover, that <placeName reg="Medford, Middlesex, Massachusetts" key="tgn,7014023" authname="tgn,7014023">Medford</placeName> was small and poor and insignificant, enveloped literally and overshadowed by its larger and more prosperous neighbor, <placeName reg="Charlestown, Boston, Suffolk" key="tgn,7015010" authname="tgn,7015010">Charlestown</placeName>.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="13" />It was scarcely more than <placeName><persName n="Cradock,Governor,,,," id="n0334.0002.00002.00002" reg="nearbymention:Cradock,Matthew,,," authname="cradock,matthew"><roleName n="Governor" full="yes">Governor</roleName> <surname full="yes">Cradock</surname></persName>'s farm</placeName>; and in <dateStruct value="1700--" full="yes" authname="1700"><year reg="1700" full="yes">1700</year></dateStruct> its population probably did not exceed <num value="200">two hundred</num> souls.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="14" />In <dateStruct value="1686--" full="yes" authname="1686"><year reg="1686" full="yes">1686</year></dateStruct> the county rate contained only <num value="14">fourteen</num> names, and the whole number of polls in <dateStruct value="1695--" full="yes" authname="1695"><year reg="1695" full="yes">1695</year></dateStruct> was but <num value="26">twenty-six</num>.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="15" />While the law passed by the <rs type="place">Colonial Court</rs> in <dateStruct value="1692--" full="yes" authname="1692"><year reg="1692" full="yes">1692</year></dateStruct> required every town of <num value="50">fifty</num> householders to support a school for reading and writing, it was not till <measure n="27years" type="date">twenty-seven years</measure> later that <placeName reg="Medford, Middlesex, Massachusetts" key="tgn,7014023" authname="tgn,7014023">Medford</placeName> made any move to establish such a school.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="16" />Lying so near <placeName reg="Boston, Suffolk, Massachusetts" key="tgn,7013445" authname="tgn,7013445">Boston</placeName>, we may feel certain that if she had had the requisite number of people she would have been obliged to comply with the law, even if reluctant to do so. Its insignificance, furthermore, may be inferred from the fact that although incorporated as a town in <dateStruct value="1630--" full="yes" authname="1630"><year reg="1630" full="yes">1630</year></dateStruct> no <num value="1">one</num> of its people seemed to be aware of the fact till about <dateStruct value="1680--" full="yes" authname="1680"><year reg="1680" full="yes">1680</year></dateStruct>,—<measure n="50years" type="date">fifty years</measure> later,—and the <num value="1" type="ordinal">first</num> white child born within its borders had become an old man of <num value="83">eighty-three</num> before it had a settled minister, and this in a thorough-going puritan settlement.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="17" />Very likely as she drew her preaching from ministers settled in the surrounding towns, and from young men studying in <orgName n="Harvard College" type="college">Harvard college</orgName>, so her brighter and more ambitious boys managed to attend the public schools <pb id="p.3" n="3" /> established in those places.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="18" />The distance was not excessive, and the boys of those days did not shrink from such a daily walk as this would require.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="19" /><q direct="unspecified">Moreover, the children of those days learned to spell work with a capital W,</q> says <persName n="Martin,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00003.00003" reg="mostcommon:Martin,nomatch:0" authname="martin"><surname full="yes">Martin</surname></persName> in his <q direct="unspecified">Evolution of the <rs type="place">Public Schools</rs> of <placeName reg="Massachusetts" key="tgn,7007517" authname="tgn,7007517">Massachusetts</placeName>.</q>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="20" />If they came <q direct="unspecified">trailing clouds of glory,</q> nevertheless <q direct="unspecified">the shades of the prison house</q> began early to close about them, and long before they became men they must have perceived <q direct="unspecified">the vision splendid die away and fade into the light of common day.</q>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="21" /></p> 
<p>We are accustomed to think and to say that our ancestors when they landed on these shores brought with them the meeting-house and the school-house, and that these were the corner-stones on which they built.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="22" />In a certain sense this is true.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="23" />They brought the meeting-house to be sure, and they gave neither sleep to their eyes nor slumber to their eyelids till they had erected a house wherein to worship <name n="God" type="God">God</name>; but the schoolhouse had to wait.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="24" />The children's day had not then dawned, only the <num value="1" type="ordinal">first</num> faint streaks of light were visible above the eastern horizon.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="25" />Neither <persName n="Plato,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00003.00004" reg="mostcommon:Plato,nomatch:0" authname="plato"><surname full="yes">Plato</surname></persName> in his perfect republic nor <persName><roleName n="Sir" full="yes">Sir</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Thomas</foreName></persName> More in his ideal state had ever dreamed of such a thing as the <rs>American</rs> common school, where every child, the poorest as well as the richest, girl as well as boy, can claim, not as a charity, but as a right, the possession of the keys of all knowledge; and for the support of which a <num value="1" type="ordinal">first</num> mortgage is held on every cent of the accumulations of every childless millionaire.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="26" />The law of <dateStruct value="1642--" full="yes" authname="1642"><year reg="1642" full="yes">1642</year></dateStruct>, while recognizing to the full parental responsibility, suggested not only the viciousness of indolence and the educative office of labor, but just as plainly indicated the state ownership of the child and its responsibility for him.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="27" /><persName n="Mann,,Horace,,," id="n0334.0002.00003.00005" reg="default:Mann,Horace,,," authname="mann,horace"><foreName full="yes">Horace</foreName> <surname full="yes">Mann</surname></persName> had not yet formulated his <num value="3">three</num> famous propositions on which the common school system of <placeName reg="Massachusetts" key="tgn,7007517" authname="tgn,7007517">Massachusetts</placeName> rests: <pb id="p.4" n="4" /> <quote rend="blockquote"> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="28" /></p> 
<p><num value="1" type="ordinal">1st</num>.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="29" />That the successive generations of men, taken collectively, constitute <num value="1">one</num> great commonwealth.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="30" /><num value="2" type="ordinal">2d</num>.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="31" />That the property of this commonwealth is pledged for the education of all its youth up to such a point as will save them from poverty and vice, and prepare them for the adequate performance of their social and civil duties.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="32" /><num value="3" type="ordinal">3d</num>.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="33" />That the successive holders of this property are trustees, bound to the faithful execution of their trust by the most sacred obligations; and that embezzlement and pillage from children have not less of criminality, and more of meanness, than the same offences perpetrated against contemporaries.</p></quote> </p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="34" />Although <num value="3">three</num> generations had lived and died and been buried on the banks of the <placeName reg="Mystic, Massachusetts, United States" key="tgn,1127517" authname="tgn,1127517">Mystic</placeName> before the <num value="1" type="ordinal">first</num> allusion to the matter of education appears on its records, we may be sure that the children had not been wholly neglected.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="35" />Domestic instruction by the mother was obliged to take the place of any public schooling, and we may be sure also that women whose hearts were brave enough to follow their husbands to this savage shore were wise enough to see that their babes were not wholly left a prey to ignorance.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="36" />And so while the husband was fighting <name>Indians</name> and wringing subsistence from a reluctant soil, the wife was seeing to it that the children learned to read the <rs type="document">Bible</rs> and repeat the catechism and obey the commandments of <name n="God" type="God">God</name>.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="37" />We may not doubt that the dame school flourished— a school, as the poet <persName n="Crabbe,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00004.00006" reg="mostcommon:Crabbe,nomatch:0" authname="crabbe"><surname full="yes">Crabbe</surname></persName> sings: <quote rend="blockquote"> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="38" /></p><l>Where a poor, deaf, patient widow sits</l> <l>And awes some <num value="30">thirty</num> urchins as she knits;</l> <l>Infants of humble, busy wives, who pay</l> <l>Some trifling price for freedom for the day.</l> <l>At this good matron's hut the children meet,</l> <l>Who thus becomes the mother of the street;</l> <l>Her room is small, they cannot widely stray;</l> <l>Her threshold high, they cannot run away;</l> <l>With band of yarn she keeps offenders in,</l> <l>And to her gown the sturdiest rogues can pin.</l></quote> <pb id="p.5" n="5" /></p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="39" />The sanded floor served as blackboard, and the same rod that struck terror to evil-doers made a very good substitute for a crayon, a bit of birch bark or a broad chip made an excellent slate, and charcoal was as good as chalk.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="40" />The home, which with their descendants seems to be so fast dying out, was the centre and source of their whole life.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="41" /><q direct="unspecified">It was the conviction,</q> says <persName n="Mayo,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00005.00007" reg="mostcommon:Mayo,nomatch:0" authname="mayo"><surname full="yes">Mayo</surname></persName> in his <q direct="unspecified">Public Schools in the <rs>Colonial Period</rs>,</q> <q direct="unspecified">that every child born into this world is the child of <name n="God" type="God">God</name>, capable of becoming a vital and useful member of society; and the corresponding obligation of the community to give to it the opportunity of that training at home, in the church, and in the school, which should send it forth at early manhood or womanhood a self-directing competent person and a reputable citizen of a self-governed state, that was at work silently and persistently below the surface.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="42" />This conviction was the corner-stone of every respectable <placeName reg="New England" key="tgn,7014203" authname="tgn,7014203">New England</placeName> home, and explains, as nothing else can, the domestic life of that people.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="43" />And out of the <placeName reg="New England" key="tgn,7014203" authname="tgn,7014203">New England</placeName> home, not from church or state, was born the early <placeName reg="New England" key="tgn,7014203" authname="tgn,7014203">New England</placeName> school.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="44" />Here was the beginning of the <rs>American</rs> common school, the most precious gift to the <rs>Republic</rs> from the genius of <placeName reg="New England" key="tgn,7014203" authname="tgn,7014203">New England</placeName>,—the stone for <measure n="250years" type="date">two hundred and fifty years</measure> so persistently rejected by the builders of other commonwealths, but in these later days now recognized as the head of the corner,—the corner-stone of the new republic that cannot be broken, but upon whomsoever it shall fall it shall grind him to powder.</q>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="45" /></p> 
<p>Their ideas of education were crude, doubtless, but they were fully abreast of the times in which they lived, when only the preacher and the politician, the doctor and the lawyer, needed to know more than to read and write; and when, if a girl knew how to spin and to rock a cradle, she had all the education that was good for her. <q direct="unspecified">Of the women,</q> says <persName n="Martin,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00005.00008" reg="mostcommon:Martin,nomatch:0" authname="martin"><surname full="yes">Martin</surname></persName>, <q direct="unspecified">whose names appear in the recorded deeds of the early part of the <num value="18" type="ordinal">eighteenth</num> century, more than <num value="0.6">sixty per cent.</num> made their mark.</q>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="46" /><pb id="p.6" n="6" /></p> 
<p>In the management of the schools the ministers took a leading part; in fact, when laymen were joined with them as visitors and examiners, the ministers looked upon it rather as an impertinence.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="47" />The school was opened and closed with prayer, and when the minister visited the school he never neglected to pray with the children.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="48" />No <num value="1">one</num> but a church member would have been allowed to keep a school, and no <num value="1">one</num> not a church member would have presumed to do so.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="49" />Perhaps the following lines from <persName n="Coote,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00006.00009" reg="mostcommon:Coote,nomatch:0" authname="coote"><surname full="yes">Coote</surname></persName>'s <q direct="unspecified">English Schoolmaster,</q> a famous manual of that day in <placeName key="tgn,7002445" n="1.000 1835" reg="united kingdom" authname="tgn,7002445">England</placeName>, may have been the substance of the <rs type="place">School</rs> Rules and Regulations: 
<text><body> 
<head>The schoolmaster to his scholars.</head> <lg type="pentameter" org="uniform" sample="complete"><lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete"> <l>My child and scholar, take good heed</l> <l>Unto the words that here are set,</l> <l>And see thou do accordingly,</l> <l>Or else be sure thou shalt be beat.</l></lg> <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete"> <l><num value="1" type="ordinal">First</num> I command thee <name n="God" type="God">God</name> to serve,</l> <l>Then to thy parents duty yield;</l> <l>Unto all men be courteous,</l> <l>And mannerly in town and field.</l></lg> <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete"> <l>Your clothes unbuttoned do not use;</l> <l>Let not your hose ungartered be;</l> <l>Have handkerchief in readiness;</l> <l>Wash hands and face, or see not me.</l></lg> <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete"> <l>Lose not your books, inkhorns, or pens,</l> <l>Nor girdle, garters, hat, or band;</l> <l>Let shoes be tied, pin shirt-band close;</l> <l>Keep well your hands at any hand.</l></lg> <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete"> <l>If broken hosed or shoed you go,</l> <l>Or slovenly in your array,</l> <l>Without a girdle or untrust,</l> <l>Then you and I must have a fray.</l></lg> <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete"> <l>If that thou cry or talk aloud,</l> <l>Or books do rend, or strike with knife,</l> <l>Or laugh or play unlawfully,</l> <l>Then you and I must be at strife.</l></lg> <pb id="p.7" n="7" /> <lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete"> <l>If that you curse, miscall, or swear,</l> <l>If that you pick, filch, steal, or lie,</l> <l>If you forget a scholar's part,</l> <l>Then must you sure your points untie.</l></lg> <l /><lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete"> <l>If that to school you do not go</l> <l>What time doth call you to the same,</l> <l>Or if you loiter in the streets,</l> <l>When we do meet then look for blame.</l></lg> <l /><lg type="stanza" org="uniform" sample="complete"> <l>Wherefore, my child, behave thyself</l> <l>So decently in all assays,</l> <l>That thou mayst purchase parent's love</l> <l>And eke obtain thy master's praise.</l></lg></lg></body></text> </p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="50" />But they were at work on foundations.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="51" />They builded better than they knew,—perhaps better in many cases than they intended,—for we may believe that <name n="God" type="God">God</name> overrules the unwisdom of the sincere and honest worker and evolves therefrom something far better than he dared to hope for. They planted industry and personal responsibility and the fear of <name n="God" type="God">God</name>; they watered the tiny plants with sweat and tears; and there have grown up and spread, till they overshadow a nation of <num value="70000000">seventy millions</num>, civil and religious liberty and universal education.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="52" />At the town meeting the most frequent matters for consideration were the preacher and the meeting-house.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="53" />The meeting-house, by the way, was literally the meeting-house where all matters secular as well as spiritual were discussed and settled.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="54" />When every citizen was a member of the church, and no other person was thought fit to vote, and when spiritual and secular affairs were all <num value="1">one</num>, this seemed the proper thing to do.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="55" />The <num value="1" type="ordinal">first</num> entry in our records concerning schools was on <dateStruct value="1719-07-20" full="yes" authname="1719-07-20"><month reg="07" full="yes">July</month> <day reg="20" full="yes">20</day>, <year reg="1719" full="yes">1719</year></dateStruct>, when the town voted to hire some meet person to keep a <orgName n="Writing School" type="school">writing school</orgName> in the town for <num value="3">three</num> or <measure n="4months" type="date">four months</measure> in the winter season, and a committee of <num value="7">seven</num> men, consisting of <persName n="Tufts,Captain,,,," id="n0334.0002.00007.00010" reg="nearbymention:Tufts,Peter,,," authname="tufts,peter"><roleName n="Captain" full="yes">Captain</roleName> <surname full="yes">Tufts</surname></persName>, <persName n="Brooks,Captain,Ebenezer,,," id="n0334.0002.00007.00011" reg="default:Brooks,Ebenezer,,," authname="brooks,ebenezer"><roleName n="Captain" full="yes">Capt.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Ebenezer</foreName> <surname full="yes">Brooks</surname></persName>, <persName n="Hall,Lieutenant,Stephen,,," id="n0334.0002.00007.00012" reg="default:Hall,Stephen,,," authname="hall,stephen"><roleName n="Lieutenant" full="yes">Lieut.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Stephen</foreName> <surname full="yes">Hall</surname></persName>, Eng<hi rend="sup">n</hi> <persName n="Francis,,Stephen,,," id="n0334.0002.00007.00013" reg="default:Francis,Stephen,,," authname="francis,stephen"><foreName full="yes">Stephen</foreName> <surname full="yes">Francis</surname></persName>, <persName n="Willis,Mister,Jonathan,,," id="n0334.0002.00007.00014" reg="default:Willis,Jonathan,,," authname="willis,jonathan"><roleName n="Mister" full="yes">Mr.</roleName> <foreName n="Jonathan" full="yes">Jno.</foreName> <surname full="yes">Willis</surname></persName>, <persName n="Dea,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00007.00015" reg="mostcommon:Dea,nomatch:0" authname="dea"><surname full="yes">Dea</surname></persName>. <persName n="Whitmore,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00007.00016" reg="nearbymention:Whitmore,John,,," authname="whitmore,john"><surname full="yes">Whitmore</surname></persName>, and <pb id="p.8" n="8" /> <persName n="Jona,Mister,,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00017" reg="mostcommon:Jona,nomatch:0" authname="jona"><roleName n="Mister" full="yes">Mr.</roleName> <surname full="yes">Jona</surname></persName>.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="56" /><persName n="Tufts,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00018" reg="nearbymention:Tufts,Peter,,," authname="tufts,peter"><surname full="yes">Tufts</surname></persName>, was chosen to treat with some person to keep said school.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="57" />Nothing came from the above action, perhaps owing to the size of the committee.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="58" />At another meeting, held on <dateStruct value="-11-30" full="yes" authname="--11-30"><month reg="11" full="yes">November</month> <day reg="30" full="yes">30</day></dateStruct>, the same year, the town voted to have a school kept in the house of <persName n="Willis,,Thomas,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00019" reg="default:Willis,Thomas,,," authname="willis,thomas"><foreName full="yes">Thomas</foreName> <surname full="yes">Willis</surname></persName>, the ensuing winter, and a committee of <num value="3">three</num> men, consisting of Eng<hi rend="sup">n</hi> <persName n="Bradshaw,,Jonathan,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00020" reg="default:Bradshaw,Jonathan,,," authname="bradshaw,jonathan"><foreName n="Jonathan" full="yes">Jno.</foreName> <surname full="yes">Bradshaw</surname></persName>, <persName n="Brooks,Captain,Ebenezer,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00021" reg="default:Brooks,Ebenezer,,," authname="brooks,ebenezer"><roleName n="Captain" full="yes">Capt.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Ebenezer</foreName> <surname full="yes">Brooks</surname></persName>, and <persName n="Willis,Mister,John,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00022" reg="default:Willis,John,,," authname="willis,john"><roleName n="Mister" full="yes">Mr.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">John</foreName> <surname full="yes">Willis</surname></persName>, was chosen to agree with some suitable person to keep a writing and reading school in town <num value="3">three</num> or <measure n="4months" type="date">four months</measure> the ensuing winter, and to make return of their doings to the town at the next town meeting.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="59" />We note in the action at this meeting that the people have diminished the size of their committee, have enlarged the curriculum of their school to include reading, have settled on a place where the school shall be kept, and instructed their committee to go ahead and to report their doings.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="60" />Evidently they are in earnest and mean to have a school kept next winter.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="61" />At a meeting held <dateStruct value="-12-11" full="yes" authname="--12-11"><month reg="12" full="yes">December</month> <day reg="11" full="yes">11</day></dateStruct> of the same year, <dateStruct value="1719--" full="yes" authname="1719"><year reg="1719" full="yes">1719</year></dateStruct>, this committee reported the name of <persName n="Davison,Mister,Henry,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00023" reg="default:Davison,Henry,,," authname="davison,henry"><roleName n="Mister" full="yes">Mr.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Henry</foreName> <surname full="yes">Davison</surname></persName> for schoolmaster for <measure n="3months" type="date">three months</measure>, and the town voted to pay him <measure n="3l." type="pounds">£ <num value="3">3</num></measure> and his board.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="62" />Whether <persName n="Davison,Mister,,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00024" reg="nearbymention:Davison,Henry,,," authname="davison,henry"><roleName n="Mister" full="yes">Mr.</roleName> <surname full="yes">Davison</surname></persName> was to board round or not the vote does not specify.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="63" />The money was to be raised by levy on the inhabitants, provided it was not furnished by voluntary subscription.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="64" />A committee of <num value="6">six</num> men was chosen to find out whether <persName n="Davison,Mister,,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00025" reg="nearbymention:Davison,Henry,,," authname="davison,henry"><roleName n="Mister" full="yes">Mr.</roleName> <surname full="yes">Davison</surname></persName> would accept the town's offer, and <placeName reg="Thomas Tufts brook">Thomas Tufts</placeName> and <placeName reg="Ebenezer Brook, Erie, New York" key="tgn,2310282" authname="tgn,2310282">Ebenezer Brooks</placeName> were chosen to collect the above subscription in case it could be collected.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="65" />At a meeting held <dateStruct value="1720-02-22" full="yes" authname="1720-02-22"><month reg="02" full="yes">Feb.</month> <day reg="22" full="yes">22</day>, <year reg="1720" full="yes">1720</year></dateStruct>, the town voted to choose a committee of <num value="5">five</num> men to select a site for a school-house to accommodate the whole town, and to report at the next meeting in <dateStruct value="-03-" full="yes" authname="--03"><month reg="03" full="yes">March</month></dateStruct>.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="66" />This committee consisted of <persName n="Tufts,Captain,Peter,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00026" reg="default:Tufts,Peter,,," authname="tufts,peter"><roleName n="Captain" full="yes">Capt.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Peter</foreName> <surname full="yes">Tufts</surname></persName>, <persName n="Dea,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00027" reg="mostcommon:Dea,nomatch:0" authname="dea"><surname full="yes">Dea</surname></persName>. <persName n="Whitmore,,John,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00028" reg="default:Whitmore,John,,," authname="whitmore,john"><foreName full="yes">John</foreName> <surname full="yes">Whitmore</surname></persName>, <persName n="Brooks,Captain,Ebenezer,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00029" reg="default:Brooks,Ebenezer,,," authname="brooks,ebenezer"><roleName n="Captain" full="yes">Capt.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Ebenezer</foreName> <surname full="yes">Brooks</surname></persName>, <persName n="Willis,Mister,John,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00030" reg="default:Willis,John,,," authname="willis,john"><roleName n="Mister" full="yes">Mr.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">John</foreName> <surname full="yes">Willis</surname></persName>, and <persName n="Richardson,Mister,John,,," id="n0334.0002.00008.00031" reg="default:Richardson,John,,," authname="richardson,john"><roleName n="Mister" full="yes">Mr.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">John</foreName> <surname full="yes">Richardson</surname></persName>, but no report of their doings appears on <pb id="p.9" n="9" /> the records of the town.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="67" />The minds of the people seem to have been suddenly turned to the subject of erecting a new meeting-house, and the school-house must wait.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="68" />The next winter <num value="2">two</num> schools were kept, <num value="1">one</num> at the east end of the town under <persName n="Davison,Master,Henery,,," id="n0334.0002.00009.00032" reg="default:Davison,Henery,,," authname="davison,henery"><roleName n="Master" full="yes">Master</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Henery</foreName> <surname full="yes">Davison</surname></persName>, and <num value="1">one</num> at the west end under <persName n="Brooks,Master,Caleb,,," id="n0334.0002.00009.00033" reg="default:Brooks,Caleb,,," authname="brooks,caleb"><roleName n="Master" full="yes">Master</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Caleb</foreName> <surname full="yes">Brooks</surname></persName>.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="69" /><persName><roleName n="Master" full="yes">Master</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Brooks</foreName></persName> was to receive <measure n="40s." type="currency"><num value="40">forty</num> shillings</measure> a month, and <persName><roleName n="Master" full="yes">Master</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Davison</foreName></persName> <measure n="4l." type="pounds"><num value="4">four</num> pounds</measure> and what he might obtain of his scholars in addition thereto.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="70" />Of the character and personality of these <num value="2">two</num> <placeName reg="Medford, Middlesex, Massachusetts" key="tgn,7014023" authname="tgn,7014023">Medford</placeName> schoolmasters nothing whatever has come down to us, so far as I have been able to discover.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="71" />To them, however, belongs the proud distinction of being the only schoolmasters whose names appear on the records of the town previous to the <rs>Revolutionary War</rs>.<note anchored="yes" place="unspecified">

<milestone unit="sentence" n="72" /> 
<p><persName n="Dean,Mister,J.,W.,," id="n0334.0002.00009.00034" reg="expanded:Dean,John,Ward,," authname="dean,john,ward"><roleName n="Mister" full="yes">Mr.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">J.</foreName> <foreName full="yes">W.</foreName> <surname full="yes">Dean</surname></persName>, librarian of the <placeName reg="New England" key="tgn,7014203" authname="tgn,7014203">New England</placeName> <orgName n="Genealogical Society" type="society">Genealogical Society</orgName>, suggests, and he is probably correct, that <persName n="Brooks,Master,Caleb,,," id="n0334.0002.00009.00035" reg="default:Brooks,Caleb,,," authname="brooks,caleb"><roleName n="Master" full="yes">Master</roleName> <foreName full="yes">Caleb</foreName> <surname full="yes">Brooks</surname></persName> was the father of <persName n="Brooks,Governor,John,,," id="n0334.0002.00009.00036" reg="default:Brooks,John,,," authname="brooks,john"><roleName n="Governor" full="yes">Gov.</roleName> <foreName full="yes">John</foreName> <surname full="yes">Brooks</surname></persName>.</p></note> </p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="73" />From this time forward to the present day we may safely conclude, I think, that <placeName reg="Medford, Middlesex, Massachusetts" key="tgn,7014023" authname="tgn,7014023">Medford</placeName> has rarely been without its public winter school.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="74" />Town meetings in which the subject of schools was to be considered, or meetings called for that special purpose, became frequent, and evidently the people were waking up to the importance of education for their children, but we hear no more about building a school-house till <dateStruct value="1730--" full="yes" authname="1730"><year reg="1730" full="yes">1730</year></dateStruct>.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="75" />On the <dateStruct value="-10-5" full="yes" authname="--10-05"><day reg="5" full="yes">5th</day> of <month reg="10" full="yes">October</month></dateStruct> in this year the town voted to build a school-house on the town land by the meetinghouse, chose a committee of <num value="5">five</num> men to attend to the matter, and then promptly refused to appropriate any money therefor.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="76" />The next year, <dateStruct value="1731--" full="yes" authname="1731"><year reg="1731" full="yes">1731</year></dateStruct>, the town repeated the performance—voted to build the school-house, and then refused to raise the money.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="77" />On the <dateStruct value="1732-01-17" full="yes" authname="1732-01-17"><day reg="17" full="yes">17th</day> of <month reg="01" full="yes">January</month>, <year full="yes">1732</year>,</dateStruct> the town again refused to raise money to build a school-house.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="78" />On <dateStruct value="1732-09-25" full="yes" authname="1732-09-25"><day reg="25" full="yes">25th</day> of <month reg="09" full="yes">September</month>, <year full="yes">1732</year>,</dateStruct> the town voted to build a school-house, to be finished the <dateStruct value="-11-25" full="yes" authname="--11-25"><day reg="25" full="yes">25th</day> of <month reg="11" full="yes">November</month></dateStruct>. <persName n="Brooks,Captain,,,," id="n0334.0002.00009.00037" reg="nearbymention:Brooks,John,,," authname="brooks,john"><roleName n="Captain" full="yes">Captain</roleName> <surname full="yes">Brooks</surname></persName> was chairman of a committee of <num value="3">three</num> to attend to the matter, and, although no appropriation was made at the time, and no allusion is made to the <pb id="p.10" n="10" /> matter at a meeting held the next <dateStruct value="-01-" full="yes" authname="--01"><month reg="01" full="yes">January</month></dateStruct>, I am inclined to think the building was erected.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="79" />From about <dateStruct value="1736--" full="yes" authname="1736"><year reg="1736" full="yes">1736</year></dateStruct> <placeName reg="Medford, Middlesex, Massachusetts" key="tgn,7014023" authname="tgn,7014023">Medford</placeName> seems to have had what may be called an annual school—that is, for <num value="7">seven</num> or <measure n="8months" type="date">eight months</measure> each year, as this year the people voted to have a school from <dateStruct value="-09-" full="yes" authname="--09"><month reg="09" full="yes">September</month></dateStruct> to <dateStruct full="yes"><month full="yes">May</month></dateStruct>.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="80" />On the <dateStruct value="1738-07-30" full="yes" authname="1738-07-30"><day reg="30" full="yes">30th</day> of <month reg="07" full="yes">July</month>, <year full="yes">1738</year>,</dateStruct> they voted to have a school for the space of a year, and <dateStruct value="1739-07-23" full="yes" authname="1739-07-23"><month reg="07" full="yes">July</month> <day reg="23" full="yes">23</day>, <year reg="1739" full="yes">1739</year></dateStruct>, they voted to have an annual school.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="81" />The hiring of the master and the care of the school was usually put in the hands of a <orgName n="Special Committee" type="committee">special committee</orgName>, as now, but for some years before the <name>Revolution</name> the selectmen were charged with that duty.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="82" />The studies pursued were very few, but they sufficed.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="83" />Reading, writing, and the fundamental operations in arithmetic—the <num value="3">three</num> R's—were all that found a place in the course of studies in those early schools.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="84" />I will spare my readers an enumeration of the things we are expected to study and teach to-day.</p> 
<p>

<milestone unit="sentence" n="85" />Beginning about <dateStruct value="1750--" full="yes" authname="1750"><year reg="1750" full="yes">1750</year></dateStruct>, at each annual meeting, after voting the minister's salary, the town immediately votes to provide a school for the ensuing year.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="86" />These were the <num value="1" type="ordinal">first</num> matters attended to. Evidently the education of their children was coming to the front.

<milestone unit="sentence" n="87" />And as we approach <dateStruct value="1776--" full="yes" authname="1776"><year reg="1776" full="yes">1776</year></dateStruct>, although the records throb with drumbeats and glisten with bayonets, there are no indications of any failing of that deep interest which from that day to this <persName n="Medford,,,,," id="n0334.0002.00010.00038" reg="mostcommon:Medford,Early,,,:1" authname="medford,early"><surname full="yes">Medford</surname></persName> has ever shown in her public schools.<note anchored="yes" place="unspecified">

<milestone unit="sentence" n="88" /> 
<p>The last warrant for town meeting issued in <name n="his Majesty" type="role">his majesty's</name> name was dated <dateStruct value="1775-03-06" full="yes" authname="1775-03-06"><month reg="03" full="yes">March</month> <day reg="6" full="yes">6</day>, <year reg="1775" full="yes">1775</year></dateStruct>, signed by <placeName reg="Richard Hall">Richard Hall</placeName>, <hi rend="italics">Town Clerk</hi>. Thus early it would seem the people of <placeName reg="Medford, Middlesex, Massachusetts" key="tgn,7014023" authname="tgn,7014023">Medford</placeName> were beginning to dream of complete independence.</p></note> </p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>